# **ASHWIN CHAFALE**

(213) 551-4836 | <u>chafale@usc.edu</u> | Los Angeles, CA – 90007 <u>https://www.linkedin.com/in/ashwin-chafale</u> | <u>https://github.com/ashwinchafale</u>

#### **SUMMARY**

Senior Software Engineer with **4+ years** of experience building data-intensive applications and tackling challenging architectural and scalability problems in the field of Health Science, Finance, and E-commerce. My interests lie in System Design, Machine Learning architecture, and Distributed Parallel Computing, and I am looking for an opportunity to work in core software development, ML/Data engineering, and related fields.

#### **EDUCATION**

### University of Southern California, Los Angeles

Aug 2021 - May 2023

Master of Science, Computer Science

• Coursework: Algorithms, Machine Learning, Natural Language Processing, Databases, Web Technologies & Mobile Apps Development, Information Retrieval & Web Search Engines, Operating Systems

# RCOEM, Nagpur - India

August 2013 - May 2017

Bachelor of Engineering, Computer Science & Engineering

- Ranked 6<sup>th</sup> in the CS department out of over 1100 students
- Coursework: Data Structures and Algorithms, Distributed Database Management, Data Warehousing, & Data Mining, Web Intelligence & Big Data

#### **SKILLS**

Languages: Python, Java, JavaScript, Scala, C/C++, SQL, Unix-shell scripting

Front-end: HTML, CSS, SwiftUI, React.js, Dart, Flutter,

ML Libraries: PyTorch, TensorFlow, Pyspark, Keras, NLTK, NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-learn, Matplotlib, Plotly

Frameworks & Libraries: Spark, Airflow, Flink, Kafka, Node.js, Spring Boot, RESTful web services, GraphQL, Flask

Databases: MySQL, Oracle, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Cassandra, Amazon Redshift

AWS Cloud Services: EC2, RDS, IAM, S3, AWS Lambda, Athena, Glue, Step-Function, Sagemaker

**Tools:** Git, Docker, Kubernetes, AWS Cloud, Unity 3D **Mobile Development:** iOS Development, Swift, Dart

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

Apple Inc.

California, USA

<u>Data Engineering Intern</u> – Research Health Software Team

May 2022 – August 2022

- Developed and maintained aggregated ETL pipelines using Spark SQL and PySpark on Hadoop file systems as part of Apple's Health Software team.
- Build an **end-to-end data application** that would allow QA/QE teams to validate the user data or detect anomalies in the user data streams uploaded by the research health app.
- Processed 10 TB of large data in a distributed parallel computing architecture and extracted meaningful features from it to promote data analytics
- Responsible for scheduling, maintaining, and orchestration of data pipeline using Apache Airflow
- Skills: Data Modeling, Data Analytics & Visualization, Workflow orchestration, and ETL processes

#### Amazon.com

Remote, India

<u>DevOps Contractor</u> – AWS Codeguru Team

April 2021 – June 2021

- Implemented **static code analysis** recommendation rules in **Java** for python files to improve code quality, application performance and detect code smells in repositories. The detection percentage of the python rules was 78 % in the amazon GitHub repository.
- Incorporated unit test in **JUnit** cases to validate python rules
- Led junior software engineering interns and collaborated with the Amazon Codeguru Seattle team for proper implementation and testing of python rules

#### **Persistent Systems**

Maharashtra, India

August 2020 – April 2021

Senior Software – Data Engineer

- Implemented **PII Data Masking** and Obfuscation Pipeline using Python on client databases. Optimized data masking pipeline performance by 50% and obfuscated 450 GB of large data.
- Ingested data from various data clusters using a combination of AWS Athena and AWS Glue to create data views to be used in BI tools.
- Worked closely with ML solution architects for proper implementation of data-preprocessing pipeline and to derive insights from the data which could be further useful for the ML models.
- Responsible for the creation of various dashboards on **Tableau** for data analytics.

#### Senior Software – ML Engineer

December 2019 – August 2020

- Responsible for deploying Facebook's Deep Learning NMT Transformer model on torch-serve (open-source tool for serving PyTorch models) and created generalized custom handlers for all transformer models enabling fast and easy deployment of the model
- Responsible for deployment and testing of various Pytorch models on container technologies like Docker & Kubernetes
- Acted as a liaison between teams in Amazon-Sagemaker and Facebook ML teams for the proper deployment of the transformer model.

### Software Engineer – Full Stack Developer

October 2017 – December 2019

- Implemented several time-critical features while migrating IBM users from mainframe-based to a **distributed computing** architecture
- Consistently deliver structured and maintainable **front-end** codes to build an intuitive user interface and reusable components on the **React.js**
- Implemented REST services by Golang with microservices architecture.
- Excellent knowledge of NO-SQL on Mongo and Cassandra DB and expertise in working with SpringlOC, SpringMVC, and SpringAOP
- Contributed to developing an event-driven and time-triggered report generation module using Java and Spring
- Leveraged Apache Spark for processing and aggregating high-volume historical data for generating reports
- Interacted with clients across various global locations like the USA, Canada, China, Australia
- Leveraged knowledge in Java, J2EE, Spring-MVC, Spring Boot, Golang, JavaScript, HTML, SQL, DOJO, Node.js, React.js

#### **PROJECTS**

# Digital Music Service Provider with Song Recommendation | HTML/CSS, React.js, Python, MySQL, Swift

- Implemented the functionality to stream music, build personalized playlists and search by artist/song/album name
- Developed a song recommender system built using item-based collaborative filtering

# Text Classification via Sentiment Analysis | Python, PyTorch, NLTK, Gensim, Numpy, Pandas

- Performed text preprocessing on 4.2M Amazon Reviews and generated self-trained Word2Vec and TF-IDF features.
- Devised 20 different Perceptron, SVM, FFN, MLP, RNN & GRU models with accuracies > 0.82 on binary & multi-class classification.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

• "Are we spreading Reach or Hate? Towards Generating Contextually Relevant Sequence of Reactions for LinkedIn". (Ashwin .C, et al.) EACL 2023 Submitted – ongoing evaluation.

# **ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Consecutively awarded **Top-Talent of the Year** award by Persistent Systems for the years 2020 and 2021
- Awarded Merit Rank Holder and Merit Scholarship by RCOEM, India August 2014